hey I'm overly Asian and in this video
I'll tell you all about capsule networks
a hot new architecture for neural nets
Jeffrey Henson had the idea of capsule
Network several years ago and he
published a paper in 2011 that
introduced many of the key ideas but he
had a hard time making them work
properly until now a few weeks ago in
October 2017 a paper called dynamic
routing between capsules was published
by Sarah saber Nicholas frost
and of course Geoffrey Hinton they
managed to reach state-of-the-art
performance on the MS dataset and
demonstrated considerably better results
than convolutional neural nets on highly
overlapping digits so what are capsule
networks exactly well in computer
graphics you start with an abstract
representation of a scene for example a
rectangle at position X 20 and y equals
30 rotated by 16 degrees and and so on
each object type has various
instantiation parameters then you call
some rendering function and boom you get
an image inverse graphics is just the
reverse process you start with an image
and you try to find what objects it
contains and what their instantiation
parameters are a capsule Network is
basically a neural network that tries to
perform inverse graphics it is composed
of many capsules a capsule is any
function that tries to predict the
presence and the instantiation
parameters of a particular object at a
given location for example the network
above contains 50 capsules the arrows
represent the output vectors of these
capsules capsules output vectors the
black arrows correspond to capsules that
try to find rectangles while the blue
arrows represent the output of capsules
looking for triangles the length of an
activation vector represents the
estimated probability that the object
the capsule is looking for is indeed
present so you can see that most arrows
are tiny meaning the capsules didn't
detect anything but two arrows are quite
long
this means that the capsules at these
locations are pretty confident that they
found what they were looking
for in this case a rectangle and the
triangle so the orientation of the
activation vector encodes the
instantiation parameters of the object
for example in this case the object's
rotation but it could be also its
thickness how stretched or skewed it is
its exact location it might be slight
translations and so on for simplicity
I'll just focus on the rotation
parameter but in real capsule Network
the activation vectors may have five ten
dimensions or more in practice a good
way to implement this is to apply a
couple convolutional layers just like in
a regular convolutional neural net this
will output an array containing a bunch
of feature maps you can then reshape
this array to get a set of vectors for
each location for example suppose the
convolutional layers output an array
containing say 18 feature maps
2 times 9 you can easily reshape this
array to get two vectors of nine
dimensions each for every location you
could also get three vectors of six
dimensions each and so on something that
would look like the capsule network
represented here with two vectors at
each location the last step is to ensure
that no vector is longer than one since
the vectors length is meant to represent
a probability it cannot be greater than
one to do this we apply a squashing
function it preserves the vectors
orientation but it squashes it to ensure
that its length is between zero and one
one key feature of capsule networks is
that they preserve detailed information
about the object's location and its pose
throughout the network for example if I
rotate the image slightly notice that
the activation vectors also change
slightly right this is called
equivariance in a regular convolutional
neural net there are generally several
pooling layers and unfortunately these
pooling layers tend to lose information
such as the precise location and pose of
the objects it's really not a big deal
if you just want to classify the whole
image
but it makes it challenging to perform
accurate image segmentation or object
detection which require precise you know
location and pose the fact that capsules
are equivariance makes them very
promising for these applications alright
so now let's see how capsule networks
can handle objects that are composed of
a hierarchy of parts for example
consider a boat centered at position X
equals 22 and y equals 28 and rotated by
16 degrees
this boat is compotes is composed of
parts in this case one rectangle and one
triangle so this is how would be rent
rendered now we want to do the reverse
we want universe graphics so we want to
go from the image to this whole
hierarchy of parts with their
instantiation parameters similarly we
could also draw a draw a house using the
same parts a rectangle in a triangle
that this arm organized in a different
way so the trick will be to try to come
to go from this image containing a
rectangle in a triangle and figure out
not only that the rectangle and triangle
are at this location and this
orientation but also that they are part
of a boat not a house
so yeah let's let's figure out how it
would do this the first step we have
already seen we run a couple of
convolutional layers we reshape the
output to get vectors and we squash them
this gives us the output of the primary
capsules we've got the first layer
already the next step is where most of
the magic and complexity of capsule
networks takes place every capsule in
the first layer tries to predict the
output of every capsule in the next
layer you might want to pause to think
about what this means that the capsules
at the primary the first layer tried to
predict what the second layer capsules
will output for example let's consider
the capsule that detected the rectangle
I'll call it the rectangle capsule let's
suppose that there are two capsules in
the next layer the house capsule and the
boat capsule
since the rectangle capsule detected a
rectangle rotated by 16 degrees
it predicts that the house capsule will
detect a house rotated by 16 degrees
that makes sense and the boat capsule
will detect a boat rotated by 16 degrees
as well that's what would be consistent
with the orientation of the rectangle so
to make this prediction what the
rectangle capsule does is simply
computes the dot product of a
transformation matrix W IJ with its own
activation vector at U at UI during
training the network will gradually
learn a transformation matrix for each
pair of capsules in the first and second
layer in other words it will learn all
the part hole relationships for example
the angle between the wall and the roof
of a house and so on
now let's see what the triangle capsule
predicts right this time it's a bit more
interesting given the rotation angle of
the triangle it predicts that the house
capsule will detect an upside-down house
and the boat capsule will detect about
rotated by 16 degrees these are the
positions that would be consistent with
the you know rotation angle of the
triangle now we've got a bunch of
predicted outputs what do we do with
them well as you can see the rectangle
capsule and the triangle capsules
strongly agree on what the boat capsule
will output in other words they agree
that a boat positioned in this way would
explain their own positions and
rotations and they totally disagree on
what the house capsule will output
therefore it makes sense to assume that
the rectangle and triangle are part of a
boat not a house now that we know that
the rectangle and triangle are part of
the boat the outputs of the rectangle
capsule and the triangle capsule really
concern only the boat capsule this
there's no need to send these outputs to
any other capsule this would just add
noise they should be sent only to the
boat capsule
this is called routing by agreements
there are several benefits first since
capsule outputs are only routed to the
appropriate capsule in the next layer
these capsules will get a cleaner input
signal
more accurate accurately determine the
pose of the object second by looking at
the paths of the activations you can
easily navigate the hierarchy of parts
and know exactly which part belongs to
which objects like the rectangle biller
belongs to the boats or the triangle
belongs to the boat and so on
lastly routing this by agreement helps
parse crowded scenes with overlapping
objects we will see this in a few slides
but first let's look at how running by
agreements is implemented in capsule
networks here I have represented the
various poses of the boat as predicted
by the lower level capsules for example
one of these circles may represent what
the rectangle capsule thinks about the
most likely pose of the boat and another
circle may represent what the triangle
capsule thinks and if we suppose that
there are many other low level capsules
then we might get a cloud of prediction
vectors for the boat capsule like this
in this example there are two post
parameters one represents the rotation
angle and the other represents the size
of the boat as I mentioned earlier post
parameters may capture many different
kinds of visual features like skew
thickness and so on or location a
precise location so the first thing we
do is we compute the mean of these
predictions this gives us this vector
the next step is to measure the distance
between each predicted vector and the
meet vector so I will use here the
Euclidean distance but capsule networks
actually use the scalar product
basically we want to measure how much
each predicted vector agrees with the
mean predicted vector use using this
agreement measure we can update the
weights of every predicted vector
accordingly
note that the predicted vectors that are
far from the mean now have a very small
weight and the ones closest to the mean
have a much stronger weight I've
represent them represented them in black
now we can compute the mean once again
or I should say the weighted mean and
notice that it moves slightly towards
the cluster towards the center of the
cluster so next we can once again update
the weights and now most of the vectors
within the cluster have turned black and
again we can update the mean and we can
repeat this process a few times in
practice you know three to five
iterations are generally sufficient this
might remind you I suppose of the
k-means clustering algorithm if you know
it okay so this is how we find clusters
of agreement now let's see how the whole
algorithm works in a bit more details
first for every predicted output we
start by setting a raw routing weight
bij equal to zero next we apply the
softmax function softmax function to
these raw weights for each primary
capsule this gives the actual routing
weights for each predicted output in
this example 0.5 each equal weights next
we compute a weighted sum of the
predictions for each capsule in the next
layer this might give vectors longer
than one so as usual we apply the squash
function and voila we now have the
actual outputs of the house capsule and
boat capsule but this is not the final
output is just the end of the first
round the first iteration now we can see
which predictions were most accurate for
example the rectangle capsule made a
great prediction for the boat capsules
output it really matches it pretty
closely this is estimated by computing
the scalar product of the predicted
output vector U hat j-jake I and the
actual product vector V J this scalar
product is simply added to the predicted
outputs raw routing weight bij so the
weight of this particular predicted
output is increased when there is a
strong agreement the scalar product is
going to be large so good predictions
will
have a higher weight on the other hand
the rectangle capsule made a pretty bad
prediction for the house capsules output
so the scalar product in this case will
be quite small and the raw routing
weights of these predicted vector will
not grow much next we update the routing
weights by computing the softmax of the
raw weights once again and as you can
see the rectangle capsules predicted
vector for the boat capsule now has a
weight of 0.8 while it's predicted
vector for the house capsule dropped
down to 0.2 so most of its output is not
going to go to the boat capsule not the
house capsule once again we compute the
weighted sum of all the predicted
outputs vectors for each capsule in the
next layer that is the house capsule in
the boat capsule and this time the house
capsule gets so little input that its
output is a tiny vector on the other
hand the boat capsule gets so much input
that its output that it outputs a vector
much longer than 1 so again we squash it
and that's the end of round 2 and as you
can see in just a couple iterations we
have already ruled out the house and
clearly chosen the boat after perhaps
one or two more rounds we can stop and
proceed to the next capsule layer in
exactly the same way so as I mentioned
earlier routing by agreement is really
great to handle crowded scenes such as
the one represented in this image one
way to interpret this image as you can
see there's a little bit of ambiguity
you can see a house upside down in the
middle however if this was the case then
there would be no explanation for the
bottom rectangle or the top triangle no
reason for them to be where they are the
best way to interpret the image is that
there is a house at the top and a boat
at the bottom and routing by agreement
will tend to choose this solution since
it makes all the capsules perfectly
happy each of them making perfect
predictions for the capsules in the next
layer the ambiguity is explained away ok
so what can you do with a capsule
network now that you know
how it works well for one you can create
a nice image classifier of course just
have one capsule per class in the top
capsule layer and that's almost all
there is to it all you need to add is a
layer that computes the length of the
top layer activation vectors and this
gives you the estimated class
probabilities you could then just train
the network by minimizing the cross
entropy loss has an irregular
classification neural network and you
know you'd be done however in the paper
they use a margin loss that makes it
possible to detect multiple classes in
the image so without going into too much
detail this margin loss is such that if
an object of class K is present in the
image then the corresponding top-level
capsule should help put a vector whose
squared length is at least 0.9 it should
be long conversely if an object of class
K is not present in the image then the
capsule should output a short vector one
whose squared length is shorter than 0.1
so the total loss is the sum of losses
for all classes in the paper they also
add a decoder network on top of the
capsule network it's just a three you
know three connected layers fully
connected with a sigmoid activation
function in the output layer and it
learns to reconstruct the input image by
minimizing the squared difference
between the reconstructed image and the
input image the full loss is margin loss
we discussed earlier plus the
reconstruction loss scaled down
considerably so as to ensure that the
margin loss dominates training the
benefit of applying this reconstruction
loss is that it forces the network to
preserve all the information required to
construct to reconstruct the image up to
the top layer of the capsule network its
output layer this constraint acts a bit
like a regularizer it reduces the risk
of overfitting and helps generalize to
new examples and that's it you know how
a
capsule Network works and how to train
it let's look a little bit at some of
the figures in the paper which I find
interesting so this is figure one
showing a full capsule network for mmm
mist you can see the the first two
regular convolutional layers whose
output is reshaped and squashed to get
the activation vectors of the primary
capsules and these primary capsules are
organized in a six by six grid with 32
primary capsules in each cell of this
grid and each primary capsule outputs an
eight dimensional vector so this first
layer of capsules is fully connected to
the ten output capsules which output
sixteen dimensional lectures the length
of these vectors is yoots
is used to compute the margin loss as
explained earlier now this is figure two
from the paper
it shows the decoder sitting on top of
the caps net it is composed of two fully
connected relu layers plus a fully
connected sigmoid layer which outputs
784 numbers that correspond to the pixel
intensities of the richens reconstructed
image which is 28 by 28 pixel the
squared difference between this
reconstructed image and the input image
gives the reconstruction loss right and
this is figure four from the paper also
interesting one nice thing about capsule
networks is that the activation vectors
are often quite interpretable
for example this image shows the
reconstructions that you get when you
gradually modify one of the 16
dimensions of the top layer capsules
output you can see that the first
dimension seems to represent you know
scale and thickness the fourth dimension
represents a localized skew if you look
at how it that number 4 is modified from
the left to the right the fifth
represents the width of the digit plus a
slight translation to get the exact
position so as you can see it's rather
clear what most of these parameters do
ok to conclude let's summarize the pros
and cons capsule networks have reached
state-of-the-art accuracy on a missed on
so far 10 they they got a bit over 10
percent error which is far from a
state-of-the-art but it's
- what was first obtained with other
techniques before you know years of
efforts were put into them so it's still
a good start
capsule networks require less training
data they offer equivariance which means
that position and pose information are
preserved and this is very promising for
image segmentation and object detection
the routing by agreement algorithm is
great for crowded scenes the routing
tree also maps the hierarchy of objects
parts so every part is associated to a
whole and it's rather robust to
rotations translations and other FIM
transformations the activation vectors
are somewhat interpretable and finally
obviously its sentence idea so don't bet
against it however there are a few cons
first as I mentioned the results are not
yet state-of-the-art on cipher 10 even
though it's a good start plus it's still
unclear whether capsule networks can
scale to larger images such as the image
net data set you know what will the
accuracy be capsule networks are also
quite slow to Train in large part
because of the routing by agreement
algorithm which has an inner loop as you
saw earlier
finally there is only one capsule of any
type in a given location so it's
impossible for a capsule network to
detect two objects of the same type if
they are too close to one another this
is called crowding and it's been
observed in human vision as well so it's
probably not a showstopper alright I
highly recommend you take a look at the
code of a caps net implementation such
as the ones listed here I'll leave the
links in the video description below if
you take your time you should have no
problem understanding everything the
code is doing the main difficulty in
implementing caps nets is that it
contains an inner loop for the routing
by agreement algorithm implementing
loops in Kerris and tensorflow
can be a little bit trickier than in pi
torch but it can be done so if you don't
have a particular preference then I
would say that the PI torch code is
probably the easiest to understand and
that's all I had I hope you enjoyed this
video if you did please thumbs up share
comment subscribe blah blah blah it's my
first real YouTube video and if people
find it useful I'm
make some more if you want to learn more
about machine learning deep learning and
deep reinforcement learning you may want
to read my Holly book hands on machine
learning with scikit-learn and
tensorflow it covers a ton of topics
with many code examples that you will
find on my github account so I'll leave
the links in the video description
that's all for today have fun and see
you next time